You're listening to TIP Daniel you've done it again You got me looking at an industry that I don't want to look at it's something Buffett would not approve so you need to explain yourself Why are we looking at an airline today? You know I'm the value guy I got to do it because I know you won't and Buffett actually keeps buying airlines So I feel pretty good with you know him having my bag. I just never fully understood why though It's so well documented that airlines are just historically bad businesses and yet Buffett can't stop buying them
Well, not all of them are that bad, right? I mean, there are these airlines, actually, in all of those industries, they are outliers that are best in class operators. And I do think I found one. So I thought, you know, I got to pitch it. All right, well, I'm intrigued. We're supposed to be talking about COPA today. So should we do it? Let's go. Since 2014, with more than 200 million downloads, we have interviewed the world's best investors, studied deeply the principles of value investing and uncovered many compelling investment opportunities.
We focus on understanding businesses and intrinsic value, investing accordingly, and sharing everything we learn with you. This show is not investment advice. It's intended for informational and entertainment purposes only. All opinions expressed by hosts and guests are solely their own, and they may have investments in the securities discussed. Now, for your hosts, Sean O'Malley and Daniel Manca. We pride ourselves on looking at so many industry.
sooner or later on this show. But there are some industries that are just generally in our too hard pile to begin with. And I realize again and again that with healthcare companies that those businesses just fall right into that bucket for me. And another industry I usually have on my blacklist is the airline industry. And I'd say they have deservedly earned one of the worst reputations and all the value investing, right? I mean, decades of bankruptcy is brutal, brutal price competition.
almost no pricing power and truly enormous fixed costs. But I'm sure you wouldn't have brought today's company as a pitch if you didn't think the economics were different for them. I wouldn't have. And you actually don't make my case easier today. But I do have a similar bias here. And I didn't think that I would have a pitch in the airline here on the show. But again, I do love best-in-class businesses. And I like them even more when I can buy them at what I consider to be a cheap valuation. And
Since most investors don't like to look at the airline industry, even the best businesses in that category tend to get punished from time to time. Those are always the interesting setups that I like to look for as a value investor. You have good companies that are being sold off because of the industry that they operate in. Just to give listeners a quick idea of why they should keep listening and why Copa, the company we're discussing today, is different from other airline competitors, you have in my view
the single most profitable airline of any real scale in the Americas trading at roughly eight times earnings. And you know, you can compare that to the US airlines like Delta like United, those usually traded multiples of, you know, 12, 13, 14, so the low teens while operating at lower margins with much more volatility in earnings. And the important thing actually is that there are structural advantages to why Copa is more profitable than all these other airlines. So
It's not just them having a good couple of years, but they actually have a value prop that in my opinion, other airlines simply can compete with. And that's why I brought Copa today as an airline to pitch you on the show. That does sound promising. You're getting me excited. But before you keep selling me on Copa as a standalone company, how about we dig a bit more into the industry? Because it really is one that we haven't looked at on the show in the past very much. And so it deserves some extra attention.
I'm certainly no expert. So when I say that the airline industry is bad, I'm mostly just looking at the historical track record of them destroying shareholder returns, which is something that Buffett has famously called out a number of times at the annual shareholder meetings. But when there are outliers like COPA, they certainly deserve a closer look so we can figure out whether they will win or whether the industry will win and suck them into their shareholder value destroying nature over time.
Well, what do you say about just Buffett giving us an intro into, you know, the airline industry and why it's such a hard place to be in? I mean, Buffett's relationship with airlines, it is quite funny. He, you know, invests in them repeatedly. Then he gets his hands burned repeatedly. And then he goes out again and buys the airline. So there's clearly something that he likes in the airline industry. And so, yeah, I would say we just listen to him ranting on the industry in general. Here it is. The airline industry.
has this situation where they have very, very, very low incremental cost per seat with enormous fixed costs. And the temptation to sell that last seat at a very low price is very high, and sometimes it can be very difficult to distinguish between the last seat and other seats.
labor-intensive, capital-intensive, largely commodity-type business. And it's been, as Bill Miller points out in that question, it's been a death trap for investors ever since Orville took off. I mean, as I've said, if there had been a capitalist, it's kiddy hockey, should have shot down Orville, and that was all a favor. But having neglected to do that,
investors have poured money into airline companies and aircraft manufacturing companies now for 100 years plus with terrible results. And if it ever gets down to where there's one airline and there's no regulation, it will be a wonderful business. And then the question is whether having gotten down now through a lot of bankruptcies to a relatively few that are doing high percentage of the seat miles, whether it's a good business yet,
I don't know the answer to, but I'm skeptical. Charlie? Well, the last time we were presented with a similar opportunity was when the railroads did exactly what Bill Miller suggests. The railroads got down and consolidated and got better control of their labor costs and it turned into a wonderful business. And what did we do? We missed it. And we stumbled in very late to the party, right? Right. So we've proven ourselves to be slow learners in this field.
And it's conceivable, isn't it? That Bill Miller is right in what he suggests. Which way do you bet? It goes into my too hard pile. Mine too. Balfour and Manga say multiple interesting things in this short clip. So the first one obviously is that they point out how capital intensive this industry actually is. And to make it a bit simpler, we often talk about operating leverage when you have a fixed cost base and low variable cost.
Scales an enormous benefit to you. So let's say you are a singer. OK. And you book a venue to give a concert where the overall cost is $2,000. Now, for simplicity, let's say you sell a ticket for, I don't know, $1. OK, wait a minute. Gosh, if any of our artists start selling tickets for $1 over a Universal Music Group, which is holding our portfolio, we're going to have real problems as shareholders, Daniel. Well, you know, that's fair. That's fair. But it's also.
It makes the math easier. So let me go with $1 here just for the sake of the episode here. So to break even, you know, if the tickets are only $1, you would need to sell 2000 tickets. But every sold ticket beyond that comes with a very high profit margin. So there are not a lot of variable costs for any one customer after that. So the more people you can bring in after you covered all the fixed costs, the more your margins improve. And that's basically operating leverage at scale and at work. So
The best businesses in the world, and we've looked at a lot of them here on the show, they benefit massively from operating leverage. So think about our portfolio company, Adobe, for example, right? Most of the cost lies in developing the product suite once and then selling one more unit or subscription in their case. And that just adds pretty much no additional cost. It wouldn't be right to talk about operating leverage and not bring up Uber. I can't help myself, right? Because they're always my case study and operating leverage.
Anybody who's ever met me at a shareholder meetup or something like that, I'm always hyping up Uber's operating leverage just because it's so incredible to me what they've been able to do. Right. So they're operating margins on that business have gone from negative 43 percent in 2020 to nearly 12 percent positive today. So everyone doing the math at home, that is a 55 percentage point swing in six years. And so they do have some incremental
insurance and driver compensation costs. But basically, as they ramp up ride volumes, revenues can be spread across their overhead and software costs. They don't scale one to one with each new ride or delivery. And so anyways, it requires a tremendous amount of volume to get to a profitable scale. But Uber has now proven that they not only can operate profitably at scale, but they can continue to improve those margins each year. And so again, to me, that is like the epitome.
of operating leverage in a business that nobody thought had operating leverage. And the same is probably true of airlines, right? You know, not so long ago, a lot of savvy investors would have argued that Uber could never generate a profit. But those naysayers dramatically underestimated the operating leverage hidden in this business model. So I wonder if that's going to be a theme today with COPPA as we discuss their potential operating leverage as a business.
Well, I think the airline industry is slightly older than ride sharing. And I think it has proven over time that generally the industry itself is just not a good place to invest in. And part of that is that operating leverage works in both directions. And with airlines, it's even worse because the upside is capped or the downside is quite big. So to give another example, let's assume you have an aircraft that has a hundred seats. Now, as you can probably imagine, there are a lot of fixed costs involved in a flight. So the two major expenses are obviously fuel and labor.
And those costs basically stay the same, whether your flight is fully booked or half empty. So let's say you need 80 people to break even on the 100 person flight. What the problem then is that every flight with a lower capacity is loss making, but at the same time, you can't seat more than 100 people. So your operating leverage is also kept with relatively low upsets, right? There's a maximum of 20 seats where you can actually make a profit from. And you also have to offer those loss making
flights just to keep the business continuity intact. If a restaurant closed its doors on any slow afternoon just because they weren't making profitable money during those hours, then people would come to not know when the business is open and would start to second guess the schedule and then they would stop going there. And it's the same thing with the airlines. There's a reliability and a consistency that has to be there. No matter whether the business is turning a profit on those flights or not,
because if they reduce their options or are canceling flights last minute, you are going to go to competitors. And so, as I'm saying here, with that competition, that just makes it even harder to make a profit because all of the airlines compete on price. And therefore, that pressure was a margin even further. To stick with this example, the low on airline has to go on pricing to stay competitive. Obviously, also the more seats it needs to fill to sell make a profit.
more and more price competition would mean that eventually you don't need 80 customers to break even but maybe 85 customers. This makes it even more likely that you will lose money on a flight and it also caps your upside even further. And this is where another disadvantage comes into play in the video a minute ago that we saw Buffett basically mentioned the problem that airlines sell their last seat at basically any price. And this is a pretty important detail because that dynamic crushes essentially
the price for every competitor. So when I booked my ticket to Markter recently to visit one of our Massaman members who actually also told me that I should cover this stock because it's interesting. I didn't care what Jelena booked the flight with, right? Like the only thing I looked for was getting the cheapest flight with the best connection. So I don't like having two stops, obviously. So, you know, direct flight or maybe one stop when it's 12 to Omaha, for example, but then the cheapest connection. So the first observation here is that flights are obviously a commodity like I don't care which brand it is.
I just care about price and the direct flight in the best case. Not a huge surprise there. And the second is that my ticket price alarm, which I actually said in this case, was going down as the 12-odd date got closer. I think the biggest issue here, Daniel, is that you didn't include me on your trip to Malta. I guess though this price alarm going down as the date gets closer, though, that's sort of an interesting thing, right? And I guess this is, you mentioned it because of the operating leverage involved here, right? You know, once the threshold for
breaking even on the flight is reached, airlines make basically 100% pure profit on each additional seat sold. So they're thinking, if I can't sell it for $200, I'd rather sell it for $100 last minute than get no money at all. Is that sort of the right way to think about it? Yes. That's basically the dynamic there. You know, when you, for example, book a hotel room and it's not sold for a single night, right? And you can still sell it tomorrow or the night after, but a seat on a flight
you can basically only make money with until, well, you know, the plane is in the air. So if it's not sold by then, the airline basically missed out on the highest margin part of the entire flight. So airlines are under this enormous pressure to fill that last seat at any price above basically zero, although, you know, technically, obviously the one or some money, but it's a significantly lower price than, you know, maybe three months ago when you booked. And that's only because of this marginal cost of carrying one more passenger being so low.
So as you're describing this dynamic, I can't help but think of our experience with our hotel rooms in Omaha recently for the Berkshire shareholder meeting right in May. You know, we obviously booked our rooms for this year's event as soon as we possibly could. It's almost a year out because usually that's how you would think that you get the best prices. But you know, this year hotel rooms around Berkshire weekend, they had this similar problem to airline seats just because the demand was
so much higher than any other time of the year, typically. But then at the same time, hotels during Berkshire or weekend in Omaha could historically be able to fill every single room. So that would be as if an airline had a fully booked flight. Then they wouldn't make tickets cheaper over time, of course, because why would they do so? They have sort of the leverage to raise prices for last minute purchases. But this time though, with Buffett not on stage,
and Greg Abel, taking over as CEO, demand was lower than expected for attendance overall. And hotels reigned into this airline problem. If they didn't sell their hotel rooms for the Berkshire Knights, then demand would be way down afterward. So they would rather just sell out all the rooms, even if the price is at a lower rate than it would have been in prior years. And so anyway, long story short, Daniel and I booked a motel for probably the price of a four-star hotel this year.
while people who waited to do their bookings at the last minute got forced our hotels at probably the same price or a better price. Yeah, that was a tough one. I gotta say that. I mean, honestly, the room itself was not too shabby. But you know, the lobby and maybe also the breakfast service wasn't exactly a four-star service. I gotta say that. And actually, I saw the same thing happening with flights as well. I think I paid 1100 bucks from a flight to Omaha last year. And if I would have just waited six or seven months, I would have gotten a significantly cheaper price. So
This time, you actually saw the same dynamic with the tail rooms and then also the airplane tickets. Come on, don't tell me that you don't think that two day old stale muffins aren't the epitome of a great breakfast, right? How about we dig a bit deeper, though, into the fixed costs so that we're not spending too much time talking about muffins? And after that, we can get to some of the reasons why Copa doesn't face the same pressures and is able to earn profits while the competition is just getting hammered.
So I think that makes sense. So we talked about the cost again, the main ones are fuel and labor. So for COPA, for example, jet fuel is about a quarter of revenue in costs. So it's a huge position at the price of it is basically set by global oil markets, which means that the airlines have no control over it. And if they are smart and or lucky, it kind of depends on who you ask, they can hedge against that with long term contracts that basically enable them to buy fuel at a certain price for a period of time.
Kopa actually has a policy against doing that against hatching. So they always buy it for the market price. And we can talk about that later on. But that's basically how you can do it. And you could certainly argue that, especially in a time like today where there's a bit more uncertainty about the pricing, it would be nice to hatch. But looking at the history and the track record of not hatching to meet appears like they generally make a good choice there. Ryan there, for example, has recently hatched its exposure to fluctuating prices, which is
what hasn't been heard as much by the current Iran conflict. So as you can see, there are two different approaches. I wouldn't say there's right or wrong. It's just, you know, whatever the culture of that company, then beyond those costs, you have many tens of millions that you pay for the fleet of, you know, the aircraft, the crew, the gate, the maintenance, all that sort of stuff. And as you said, that's basically all happening regardless of how many tickets you actually sell for a flight. And you definitely got to take that flight because if I just go to the airport and they say, oh,
We only sold 50 tickets and it's not making any sense for me anymore. We cancel the flight. That's obviously terrible customer service. So one other thing that I have to say, and I promise after this, I'll give you the opportunity to tell us why Copa is different. But looking at the airline industry, you just don't have the normal, natural, healthy cleanup mechanism that happens with bankruptcies. With Forrest, it's important to have these targeted burns.
to get rid of a lot of the dead wood because otherwise it accumulates. And then when there is a fire, it's much, much worse. You get this massive wildfire. And that's sort of what I'm imagining here. That's a metaphor that people use for a lot of financial crises of these targeted burns to clear out the brush so that you have a healthier ecosystem overall. And you don't have that with airlines, right? And Buffett and Munger mentioned how railroads
became much better businesses to own after a number of consolidations and bankruptcy has happened and these bad operators were taken out of the picture. And when airlines go bankrupt though, the airline is often saved or restructured. And then it's just business as usual from there, right? I mean, we just seen this happen with spirit and some other smaller airlines have been bailed out by the government after the fuel price increases brought them to the verge of bankruptcy and
you can see why this happens. There's like a too big to fail dynamic here, right? Airlines are essential to the global economy. And actually, I know you know the story, Daniel, I found myself at the center of this problem when my airline to Denmark went bankrupt right before I was making a business trip to visit our colleague Stig. And you know, let's just say that caused a lot of stress. The longer that operations are halted,
the more people are impacted. And so it does become a compounding problem so you can see why governments are so quick to want to step in and help out. You know, usually it's not an advantage to live in Germany if you work for TAP and you think in terms of traveling. Because most of the time it goes into the States and I have all the terrible travel stories. But you know, I'm visiting Stig next week and I'm fortunate enough to have a pretty short trip. So I'm just taking the train. You know, there's no stress with catching any planes or any airlines going bankrupt. But
Yes, basically what you described is a pretty vital part of the industry and it's generally another one of these vicious cycles in the island industry. Usually you benefit when a competitor goes bankrupt, but when an airline goes bankrupt, as you said, its planes usually get sold cheaply to somebody else, a competitor of yours, which once again fuels the pricing battle. All the airline just restructures its debt and sheds its obligations and comes back.
roaring out of you know, chapter 11 bankruptcy. And then it's basically leaner than the competitors who actually paid their bills and were struggling to get through this phase or recession, for example. So the discipline that fixes other industries doesn't really work the same way with airlines. And then, you know, capital keeps getting destroyed. And then, you know, capital keeps coming back for more. This is basically what Buffett described in this video as his bottomless pit, which basically the other industry is.
We've actually seen what happens when an industry does go through that cleanup with the railroads business as we mentioned and as Buffett and Munger have talked about at length, right? Buffett went big on B and SF because railroads basically finished their bankruptcy phase decades ago and consolidated down to a handful of players. And then you shift to an oligopolistic industry structure and the economics look very, very different, right? Those players got disciplined, the economics improved thanks to scale.
And so railroads used to be just as bad as airlines. Too many operators, brutal pricing, everyone going under, too much debt. And then they just got down to four or five disciplined operators working at scale without these kind of pesky, unprofitable operators on the margins ruining their business. And the whole dynamic flipped. And somehow airlines just never got there. So that's really something I would be so curious to wrap my head around more.
Well, Bill Miller, who most of all he has probably familiar with actually bet on exactly that happening with airlines to repeatedly invested in airlines in I think was 2008 and 2013 calling, you know, an airline Renaissance driven by industry consolidation. Basically what we've seen with railroads. It played out to some extent, but certainly not on the scale of railroads and you know what Buffett has experienced there.
I mean, he continued investing in airlines again and again, Buffett did so as well. So I believe that some investors still hope for that to happen. And you've actually seen somewhat of a shift toward that actually happening and playing out. But then COVID came along and also kind of reshaped the entire industry again. So it just keeps being pretty volatile and just uncertain place to be in. Let's take a quick break and hear from today's sponsors.
One part of being an investor that I don't think gets enough attention is how hard it can be to continue to improve as an investment researcher. And for myself, I often find that when I finish a great conversation with some industry expert or fund manager, my head is full of ideas. But by the time I sit down to write it all up, half of them are already gone. That's why I've been using Plod Note Pro.
It's a small device that sticks to the back of my phone and captures the conversation and hands me back a clean, searchable recap. And so the key points, the follow-ups, the things I usually want to act on, it has all of that. And that allows me to stay present in the room and set a scribbling notes that I won't be able to read back later. And I notoriously have very bad handwriting. And so it's changed how I prep and how I follow up with investors. It's also built for people who take conversation seriously. Enterprise grade security.
So if you're recording calls with clients or industry contacts, that's covered too. So if you live in meetings, calls and interviews, we'll give it a look. Go to plod.ai slash WSB and use code WSB for 10% off. That's plod.ai slash WSB code WSB and always get consent before you record a conversation.
Curious about online trading but haven't taken the first step yet? You're not alone. And Plus 500 futures is a great place to start. The futures markets are moving fast and with Plus 500 you can explore popular assets like oil, gold, S&P 500, Bitcoin and more. From crypto to commodities, there's always something happening. The platform is super easy to use so you can trade on the go right from your phone. You can get started with just $100 and jump into the action.
See something interesting? Once your account is open, you can trade it in just a couple of clicks. And if you're not quite ready yet, you can practice with a free demo account. No risk, no pressure. With 20 years of experience, plus 500 makes trading more accessible than ever. Check it out at plus500.com. Trading and futures involves risks of loss and is not suitable for everyone. Not all applicants will qualify. Plus 500. It's trading with a plus.
They say every day your business is late to AI, you fall two days behind in the competition, they're only moving faster. Fortunately, there's NetSuite Next. You probably already know NetSuite, the AI-powered business suite that securely connects all your data, financials, inventory, commerce, HR, and CRM all in one source of truth trusted by over 43,000 customers. NetSuite Next is the next huge leap
because now AI is built into everything you do. It surfaces custom insights throughout your day. AI agents work alongside you on the routine stuff. And anytime you've got a question about anything, you just ask like you're talking to a colleague and I use it. And really, I think you should too. For the first time ever, you can try NetSuite next for free. If your revenues at least in the seven figures go to net suite dot AI slash TIP built for every industry, ready for every boardroom.
net suite.ai.com. All right, back to the show. We were talking about this before the recording, but we have a tremendous amount of respect for Bill Miller. And he is actually a friend of the show, and he's been on the podcast previously. So when he makes a statement like this with his investments, it's something we pay attention to. And there does seem to be something about airlines that has attracted super investors repeatedly. And
I think it's good that you bring it up now because up until now, we've probably thoroughly convinced our audience never to touch this sector, which is probably not the best way to start a pitch for a stock that is in this sector. So maybe we can turn things around. You know, if the industry is this structurally cursed, how does anyone make money? Because some companies, and especially Copa, clearly have, as I'm sure you'll tell me here shortly.
I will. I mean, I definitely have to say this is by far the hardest pitch I've ever done. Right. The other industry is just a tough one to convince people of, but I do think there are a few ways to make money. So the most powerful one, and we already touched on that with Reiner is just being the cheapest player. If everyone is selling an identical product and prices keep getting pushed down to the floor, the only player who survives that floor and actually is making money there is the one with the lowest cost base. So Reiner in Europe and perhaps Southwest back in its prime at least in the US.
So these are the airlines that have consistently reinvented what is expected from an airline and saved costs wherever it's possible. And the second one, which I personally find even more interesting is owning a network position that competitors just can't copy. So that could be an airport where these slots are constrained and you control most of them or, and this is actually the game that Copa plays, a geographic position where it doesn't make economic sense for a rival to even try to fly the same route.
We will get into that into detail later, but then there's also a third way that you can make money and be profitable. And that is a restructured competitive field. So the reason you know these big US airlines became investable for a period and the reason you know Buffett of all people and then also Bill Miller got interested in them is because for a short period of time, this is what I said a minute ago, it looked like there will actually be mergers and you know consolidation in this industry. And then as I said, there was kind of, you know, COVID coming in and making it a bit more difficult.
But that's not what happened, right? I mean, at least not in the US. Yeah, it did not. I mean, again, Berkshire bought the four big US airlines. And then in the spring of 2020, again, COVID grounded the entire world. And Berkshire went out and so on. Its entire basket obviously had a loss and basically said that the world has changed for airlines and probably for good. So even the most disciplined version of this industry, which it probably has been before COVID,
can take out of the woodchip by a single exogenous shock. So to be fair, I would say personally that many, many industries were hit hard when COVID happened. Obviously, airlines were certainly up there, but I mean, pretty much all industries were not selling things, except for the e-commerce players, maybe. But it was a tough period for all of them. And we did see travel, and we talked about it in our Transom episode. We did see travel pick up quite significantly after COVID. So I didn't think there was lasting damage to the industry.
Now, I don't think there was a single industry that was probably hit harder than the airlines during the pandemic, right? Like it's, it's hard to imagine one at least for me. But I do want to ask you about this other thing that I've always thought about when I fly. And it's these loyalty programs and that sort of stuff. How does that factor in here? Right? I mean, did that change the airline industry for the better? Right? Whenever I fly, it's kind of amazing and also annoying to me all the things that I can book.
in addition to my seeds, right? You're trying to sell me on like extra luggage, better Wi-Fi, priority boarding, which I've never really cared about. Economy Plus, Economy Super Plus, whatever that means. And then all these different miles programs, I just can't help but think like they wouldn't be doing this if it didn't have some sort of positive impact on the economics, right? Yeah, I think so. I actually thought about this just last time when I traveled back from Montana and there were all these different things that you could buy. And as you said,
I don't know who pays for faster morning. I just don't seem to think that it makes any sense. I mean, I was getting told that you can get your luggage in better positions. I don't know. Maybe that's true. I probably won't spend an extra dime on that. But yes, generally, these frequent flyer programs, the miles and especially the cobra and the credit cards, that in partnership with these big banks and are coming out more often, those actually make the island industry slightly better. So it's basically the first thing that is introducing somewhat of a switching cost mode.
into this industry and obviously it's high margin, you know, it's relatively stable. And again, like probably the only thing I can think of that gives it somewhat of a switching cost mode. If I have a miles program with, you know, United, most of the time that I fly to, for example, Omaha on New York City, I would choose United so I can get some miles on my carton. I actually recently talked to a friend who told me that he pays for two vacations a year just with the miles that he earns from flying. So I don't know, but now I'm flying so much that I'm thinking
I maybe should give more thought to optimizing my my ads and loyalty programs than I currently do. I should probably ask you, I mean, knowing how you trick the system with all your credit cards, you probably have some good tips for me on how I do the same with miles. No Daniel loves to tease me because I'm always looking for these like personal finance hacks and they've worked pretty well for me. I got to say it is funny that you mentioned it because I don't think I've ever actually paid for a trip with miles though. And maybe it's just because I'm a value investor, but I love to know exactly how much
I'm getting back. So I always opt for the cashback cards where it's like, you know, you get 2% back, right? You spend $100, you're getting $2 back, right? Very tangible. I can understand that. But whenever you have these miles programs, they have these like crazy conversion rates and I have no idea they're like, you know, if you spend this amount of money, you get 50,000 miles or points. I'm like, what does that mean? It drives me crazy. And so I just get lost.
And I don't know, I want to know simply how much cash am I going to have in hand? What is this worth? And yeah, that's always been my approach to credit cards. But now I have a card that allows me to earn points on my mortgage payment and, you know, without any transaction fees. And so I might be redeeming those soon for a trip. You know, maybe I'll have to come out to Hamburg and use some miles to do it. But to get back on track, I mean, let me take a shot at.
summarizing what we discussed up until now. We've covered a lot of ground. The airline industry has historically destroyed capital due to commoditization, perishable inventory, fixed costs, fuel costs, and cyclicality. And the handful of ways to beat that are really just to be the low cost producer, own an uncopiable network position, operate in a very disciplined market structure,
You'll milk out these loyalty programs and then carry a balance sheet that is strong enough to outlast any of these, you know, cyclical crises that emerge. And that's essentially why I'm pitching Copa today, because I do believe that Copa isn't just one of those things. It's actually all of them. I mean, they are the lowest cost network carrier in the Americas. They sit in a geographic position that I don't see anyone replicate and they've got by far the strongest balance sheet in Latin America and aviation, which
is also where they were the one airline in that region that didn't go bankrupt during COVID. So I think you better understand why and how Copa is actually different. I guess it makes sense to take a look at its history. So it was founded back in 1947 as the National Airline of Panama. For us, though, it starts to get more interesting about 40 years ago when Pedro Halbron became the CEO of the company. And the remarkable part about that is that he is still CEO today, 38 years later, which is
pretty much unheard of in the industry. And why is not a founder attend you this long, in my opinion, at least to some extent makes up for that. No, I think that counts. I'm just trying to think here. Do we have any companies in our portfolio with the CEO who's been at the company for longer than that? It's such a rare thing to find. Yeah, maybe not anymore. I mean, last year, we could have still pointed to Berkshire, obviously.
And we looked at some companies that came close, like Mark Leonard at Constellation Software, for example. But I don't have anyone in mind right now. Oh, it's true. Well, we do have Andy Florence of CoStar actually. He tops that, right? He's been the CEO for something like 40 years. So I don't know how we could forget that. And when I think about the companies we've covered where the operating culture is really durable, like a Mark Leonard at Constellation Software for 30 plus years or a Buffett at Berkshire for 60 years or
Bernardo no at LVMH since what the late 80s. And they all kind of have one thing in common, right? There's this one person who has been steering the strategy for decades and just refused to change course, right? And very, very high conviction. And again, that was one of the things we liked about co-star and why we own it in our portfolio, even though it's a smaller position. And it's the consistency that you can get from that can really be enough to dominate some of the toughest industries.
You just don't get that from a CEO who's coming in as an outside consultant or that's trying to hit a number for the next bonus cycle. Usually having these long tenured CEOs means that they own a meaningful chunk of equity. And so they have skin in the game and that goes hand in hand with how they run their business. There's a mindset. There's a principal agent dilemma that gets solved if you have a founder CEO with significant skin in the game.
running the business truly on behalf of shareholders because they themselves are massive shareholders. And that is certainly also true for Copa. But since the structure is somewhat complex, I would suggest that we save that for later. Just for now, they do own the entire management team. It's a pretty significant chunk of the equity and the economic interest in the company. If we take another look at Copa's history for now, there was another big turning point because in 1998, continental airlines, which was this,
big US carrier at the time took a minority stake in Copa. And that partnership basically gave Copa the template for the hub and spoke model on which they then build the entire future. And that United relationship that everybody associates with Copa today, as I understand it, where does that come from? Is that related to this original partnership they had with Continental? That was part of the United and Continental merger, which happened in 2010.
So, COPA's old continental alliance simply became a United Alliance. And then in 2012, COPA formally joined the so-called Star Alliance, which is, you know, this global airline grouping anchored by United. That's pretty important, actually, because the Star Alliance membership of United is actually a big part of why Panama works so well as a hub for travel, especially coming out of the United States. So walk me through the actual business here. You mentioned that the core of COPA
is that it's a hub and spoke connector. And so what does that actually mean? Right? I mean, that's some real jargon there. Also, why is that a better position to be in compared to the more traditional business model for airlines? Yeah, so a hub and spoke model is basically a routing system where one central airport acts as the primary transfer point. So for example, Chicago is one of United's hubs in the US. So whenever I fly to Omaha, I go through Chicago,
And for Copa, the whole business is really about these connecting flights because they have a pretty special spot in Panama. So Panama sits right at the nearest point of the whole American continent, basically the geographic center of the hemisphere where North America funnels down to meet South America and Copa's home airport, Tokumen, sits at the sea level pretty much in the middle of that. So they fly somewhere like 85 cities in over 30 different countries.
north and south and they route all of them through that one airport. I definitely can see how that location then seems like an advantage compared to other airlines and hubs. But is that so much of an advantage that they have a structurally more profitable business? I mean, as you mentioned, all the big airlines have their hubs too. And there are these strategic advantages that come with them. That's true. But the location actually creates massive cost benefits for Copa. And I'm actually, I'm getting quite excited about this. I think I told you before that
I just love diving into the industry and I didn't expect that before I did it. So due to the positioning, Copa can use Boeing 737s, which are these small, cheap and also the most efficient planes to reach essentially every single one of those 85 destinations from, I don't know, Buenos Aires in the deep south to Toronto in the far north without a payload penalty. Payload penalty. I have to say, I think we were both buzzing with excitement to do this call because.
it's something new for us. And you know, if you've covered 70 plus businesses, you know, things can get repetitive. And one of the interesting things about our pitches, though, is that there is always something new that we learn and would have never otherwise thought about. And so I have absolutely no idea what a payload penalty is. And I figure you probably had no idea what that was until like maybe two weeks ago. But I can feel the excitement in you as you talk about
you know, how cobra is shielded from the Bayload penalty. It's interesting. As you said, two weeks ago, I didn't know about it. But yeah, again, I told you before the call that I really enjoyed diving into the airline industry. So I think it's just one of those things that we all know as consumers. And many investors obviously know that it's supposed to be this bad business. But few people actually know the economics behind it and why it is the way it is. And I just love to learn those things, right? Like how do they work? I would say that you sort of
understand how the world works one company at a time. I feel like that's what we're doing here week in week out. But anyway, to answer your question of what a payload penalty is, basically every plane has a maximum weight that it's allowed to take off at and that weight has to cover obviously the plane itself, the fuel and everything paying, which means, you know, passengers, bags and cargo. So on a long route, you need so much fuel on board that there's less weight left over for the paying load.
So, you know, cargo and even passengers, for example. So in practice, that means the airline carries less cargo in the belly. And on the very longest routes, they actually have to sell fewer tickets than the plane can physically hold. Because if they sold every seat and loaded all the fuel needed, the plane would literally be too heavy to take off. So the longer the route, the more revenue you literally leaving on the ground. And Copa's geographic basically sidesteps.
that whole problem because Panama is so central again. None of coppers flights are actually ultra long haul. So there are all these medium length hops radiating out from the middle. So Copa gets to serve this continent spanning long haul looking network using these small, you know, cheap single aisle planes, the Boeing 737, whereas if a competitor tried to connect, say North America and South America directly,
They would need big expensive white body jets to do it just because they're not located in Panama. There's also this compounding thing going on, which honestly looks like a form of network effect when I look at it. So every new destination, Copa adds to the hop doesn't just create one new route. It actually creates a whole lot of new routes, right? Many and many of them. So if copper adds, I don't know, Puerto Igua, Zua in Argentina, which is a destination they currently don't have, but I actually working on getting that on boarded.
Then you can fly from dozens of different countries and starting points to Puerto Rico-Azure, not just one point. So it sounds obvious, I know, but that's a pretty big thing for the economics. So COPA generates over 5,000 marketable city pairs out of those 85 destinations. That's what we're talking about here. Oh my gosh. You're really getting me excited here. I had no intention of being so excited about an airline stock heading into this, but I know you're getting me fired up and
I mean, the network effect here reminds me a little bit of COSR, right? Every new property added to COSR's database makes the platform a little more valuable for existing customers. And so the value of the network compounds faster than the inputs, basically. And it's similar for COPA, where each new destination COPA adds, it's not just one new route, right? It adds a connection to every other city already in the network. And so I don't know, it's pretty cool to see that dynamic.
in an airline, right? It's not really a mental model. I would have been able to apply if we hadn't have studied a lot of the businesses that we have. And so with all that, how about we dig a bit deeper into the financials here? Because to be honest, I only have a vague idea of what the revenue breakdown of an airline should look like and what the margins would actually be for the business. And that comes with some biases about having been told about what a terrible business
airlines are and I don't think that's entirely true with Copa. Well, the revenue is actually as simple as one would think. So the overwhelming majority, which is around 95% of revenue is from selling seats to passengers. Then only about 3% is cargo and the last 2% or so is all the rest. So, you know, that's where you find the loyalty program, for example, the great thing about cargo and let's call them value-added services or loyalty and all that sort of stuff is that they are high margin.
So when Copa flies a passenger 737 from one city to another, the belly of that aircraft has space in it, which is sold to ship freight. And since it comes at no additional cost, that's pretty high margin revenue rate. So Copa has also been leaning into cargo more deliberately lately. So they've added, you know, dedicated freighter aircraft and cargo revenue has been growing quite nicely. I think we talk about 20% year over year in recent quarters.
it's still obviously small in the overall picture again, it's only 3% of the total, but it's basically free optionality, right? It's up that you just, you know, get by buying Copa. It's not something that you bet on. I think it's pretty similar. So Copa's loyalty program is called connect miles. And because Copa is part of this United Star Alliance, those miles plug into the whole global alliance, which makes them way more useful as if it would just be, you know, this small Panamanian airline. So on its own,
a frequent flyer program is maybe a nice loyalty tool, but the real money is, as I said before, in this co-branded credit card. And that's the deal where a bank issues a copper-branded card and customers spend on it basically everywhere. And then the bank pays copper for the miles that those card holders earn. But for both of these segments, the problem is that they're pretty tiny, right? I mean, even when the core business only grows mid-single digits, you've got cargo growing at 20% plus.
It's going to take a long time before that actually starts impacting overall revenue. And so I can imagine that also that there's still a limit to how much growth is achievable here, right? Since you only have so much space on a plane, you're operating with a very finite resource. And I would think in a way that it's similar to with the loyalty program. Yep. That's completely right. I mean, you can buy Copa thinking you will see some mix shift that turns this into
only high margin credit card business of which we own enough anyway. So you're still buying an airline at the end of the day. That's true. So I know that some of our mastermind members have really wanted to see us cover Ryanair, which is also famous for being one of the few profitable airlines. And it's probably known as maybe being the most efficiently run airline out there. And, you know, they have a bit of a reputation for that efficiency. So that has led to them having a very interesting
social media presence, right? Where they joke a lot about the accommodations that they cut out for passengers. And it's become sort of a meme online. But how does Reiner's efficiency and profitability profile compare to Copa? I imagine Copa can't beat them on the social media front. But with the actual business, how does it compare? Is Copa similarly efficient?
Or does it not need to be as extreme in cost cutting thanks to these competitive advantages that it already has in terms of the business positioning? So it can compete on the social media phone, probably the only company that can is Duolingo, which is also quite good at it. But yeah, this was actually one of the more interesting things that I came across when I started looking at it. So airlines already put a metric called CASM, which stands for cost per available seed mile.
basically what it costs the airline to fly one seed, one mile. And there's a version of this called X fuel chasm, which is the same number, but obviously with the fuel cost taken out. And that's the one that actually matters when you're comparing our lines. And as you can see, if you look at the numbers for copper, they are better than 95% of airlines on that metric. So why strip out the fuel costs, though? Because that is a real cost, right? Like, why would you not want to account for that? It is a real cost, but every airline pays
pretty much the same per gallon for fuel because you know the price is set by the global oil market as I said before and none of them really controls it. So what that means is that fuel costs go up and down for the entire industry at the same time depending on where oil is trading. So if coppers total cost looks great in one year and then bad in the next that mostly just tells you about whether oil was cheaper or expensive that year. So it doesn't really tell you anything about whether copper is actually a better or worse run.
business. So to figure out which airline has the better cost structure, you got to look at everything except fuel. And that's essentially what X fuel chasm gives you. So Copa is currently at about 5.8 cents. And to put that into context, the only other airlines that I'm aware of that operate below six cents are right now, which you mentioned and with air. And then I think they're also two pretty small Latin American airlines that also operate sub six cents. And Copa has been
at that level for years now. So the fuel spike, the Max 9 grounding, which was a time in 2024 where a lot of those planes, especially the Boeing ones, had to stay on ground. All of that and even global wage inflation, all of that couldn't bring down the margins that Copa was earning and didn't spike their cost structure. So it's not just one lucky year. It's actually something that they've built into the way their airline operates. And they've done that by only flying one family of aircraft. This is what it sounds like.
the Boeing 737. And I imagine that saves a ton on cost because they only need one type of pilot training, one set of spare parts to use, one really overall maintenance procedure. And so if you compare that to a United or an American, they've got Boeing's, they've got air buses, they've got regional jets, they've got wide body jets, and they have to maintain all of that in parallel. So you just imagine how complicated and expensive
the maintenance and the servicing and all of those different variables come in and Copa just really doesn't have to deal with that. It's certainly complex. We also have a member who's a pilot and I don't want to say anything about the airline just because I don't know if we're allowed to. But he told me when I told him that I will cover an airline that he just does not understand how they can make it happen that planes actually go up in the sky and come down on schedule all the time because he says there's so many things that go wrong all the time that
You know, him just sitting in the airplane, he has no idea how all of that works out, which I don't know if he's on the ground every single day is not the most encouraging thing that he could have said. But another advantage Copa has that Ryan Air, for example, doesn't have and especially over the US carriers is labor costs. So Panamanian wages are obviously lower than US or EU wages. And in 2025, Copa's wage bill was about 14 percent of revenues. And a big US airline would usually spend about 25 percent of revenue.
on those wages. And since most of Kopa's customers aren't Panamanian, but just connecting through Panama on their way somewhere else, Kopa is actually benefiting because they're collecting international ticket prices, which tend to be higher from a global customer base while paying Panamanian wages to its crew. That's another global advantage for them. And then there's the so-called completion factor, which I honestly hadn't even thought much about before I started researching all of this.
And the completion factor basically shows you how many flights actually go into the sky and make it to the ground safe. Of course, that's what it says. Let's take a quick break and hear from today's sponsors. Curious about online trading but haven't taken the first step yet? You're not alone. And Plus 500 futures is a great place to start. The futures markets are moving fast and with Plus 500 you can explore popular assets like oil, gold, S&P 500, Bitcoin and more. From crypto to commodities.
There's always something happening. The platform is super easy to use so you can trade on the go right from your phone. You can get started with just $100 and jump into the action. See something interesting? Once your account is open, you can trade it in just a couple of clicks. And if you're not quite ready yet, you can practice with a free demo account. No risk, no pressure. With 20 years of experience plus 500 makes trading more accessible than ever, check it out at plus500.com.
Trading and futures involves risks of loss and is not suitable for everyone. Not all applicants will qualify. Plus 500. It's trading with a plus.
Most leaders have a clear picture of how work is supposed to get done in almost no visibility in how it's actually happening day to day. I felt this running our own team. Someone walks you through a process and it sounds clean, but watch it happen in real time and it looks completely different. Nobody's doing anything wrong. The gap between how we think work happens and how it really happens is just bigger than most of us realize. And without that visibility, you're deciding what to fix or automate based on gut feel, not data.
That's exactly the problem today's sponsor, Scribe was built to fix. Scribe Optimize is a workflow AI platform trusted by 94% of the Fortune 500. It passively captures how your team works across your approved business apps, no interviews, no manual process mapping and follows workflows wherever they go, even when they start in one tool and finish in another. The dashboard shows you what's happening and where the time is going. It's live right now, not a report that someone built last quarter.
and its top issues view doesn't just flag your biggest inefficiencies. It tells you why they're happening and gives AI powered recommendations with estimated time savings built in.
Importantly, it is a leadership visibility tool, not employee monitoring. It only runs on apps your admin approves, user data is anonymized by default, and sensitive information never leaves your firewall. To see Optimize in Action, head to scribe.how.wsb and mention for a 30-day risk-free trial. That's S-C-R-I-B-E.how.wsb.
They say every day your business is late to AI, you fall two days behind in the competition, they're only moving faster. Fortunately, there's NetSuite Next. You probably already know NetSuite, the AI-powered business suite that securely connects all your data, financials, inventory, commerce, HR, and CRM all in one source of truth trusted by over 43,000 customers. NetSuite Next is the next huge leap
because now AI is built into everything you do. It surfaces custom insights throughout your day. AI agents work alongside you on the routine stuff. And anytime you've got a question about anything, you just ask like you're talking to a colleague and I use it. And really, I think you should too. For the first time ever, you can try NetSuite next for free. If your revenue is at least in the seven figures, go to net suite dot AI slash TIP built for every industry.
ready for every boardroom net suite dot a i slash t i p. All right, back to the show. I know you have some experience with flights that don't make it off the ground, Daniel. You won't let that go, although you now also have the Denmark experience. It's just for context for the audience. Last year when we traveled to Omaha, I was cancer on, I think was three flights initially and you know, eventually had to spend the next one night in Frankfurt and was canceled even on my next flight the next day for which I woke up at five a.m. in the morning.
only to start flying six hours later. But yeah, you know that it was brutal. It was brutal. And I think I also mentioned it here on the podcast like six times, but I would should show you the PTSD I got from this experience. So yeah, unfortunately, you know, I've got plenty of personal experience with that. But it's not just annoying for the passenger. It actually costs the airline a whole lot of money. So from what I read, a single cancellation can cost the airline something like 25 to $60,000.
Once you add up the crew, you've already paid the rebuking hotels, as for example me, the surrender passenger in this case, all of that. And the plane never took off. So you made zero revenue on it, obviously. And on top of that, you spend a bunch of money cleaning up the mess. So in this industry, the most profitable carrier is actually just the one that consistently brings its planes into the air and obviously self down again.
Copa is one of the best in the world at this. They are at a completion rate of about 99.8%. So out of every 1000 flights scheduled, only two don't happen. Ryan is also in a similar range. I think the big US legacy carriers tend to be at around 97 to 98%. And you might think, well, okay, 99.8% compared to 97%. What's the big deal? But because airlines run so many flights, that gap is actually huge in practice. So if a carrier
of copper size ran at 97% instead of 99.8%. That's like 28,000 extra cancellations every single year. So at 40 grand a pop, you talk about a billion dollars in extra costs just from cancellations. So this thing that sounds like a small operational detail is actually one of the biggest cost differences in the entire business. So scary to think about how quickly all of these profits can just evaporate.
And at the same time, there's no reason to believe that rate should go down in Copa's case. From everything you're telling me, it almost sounds like too good to be true considering we're still looking at an airline after all. But for me, it's all about figuring out the moat today, which is kind of cliche, but it is an important thing to think about. We know that the barriers to entry in the airline business are actually low, even though you might initially ask yourself, why? Because it's such a capital intensive industry, you would think
that the barrier century would be very high. I wouldn't know where to begin. We're starting an airline business tomorrow, but I have heard that it's actually comparatively easy to get financing for an airline compared to other projects of similar sizes. And why is that? Well, banks like to lend when there are high quality physical assets to lend against that are backing up the value of the loans. And so in this case,
You couldn't really have higher quality collateral to lend against than new aircraft, right? These are very valuable assets that have long lifetime uses. And so the depreciation is relatively slow. At least compared to, you know, you buy a car and then you drive it off the lot. And the old joke is that it loses half its value. And, you know, as Buffett once said, there are a lot of people who want to be involved.
in the airline industry. And that's why it keeps attracting capital. And so let's go ahead and jump to some comments that Buffett has made on that. And people love doing it. It's exciting to people. And you can sell the idea. I've had probably a dozen proposals over the last 25 or 30 years from people that want to get into the airline business one way or the other. And the number of them have. It's sexy for some reason. I mean, it
You know, if you go to the office of some Mr. Big CEO and say, I want to talk to you about this new airplane, you get in the door, you know, I mean, if you want to talk to him about hauling coal or something is a little different. So it is a business that attracts people and you can go out and raise money for a new airline. So when I look at a map, I see Costa Rica and perhaps Nicaragua that could have a similar geographical advantage over other airlines.
So my question is, is that a threat that could challenge Copa's business model and their competitive advantages if somebody goes to one of these other geographies and just copies their playbook? Actually, the first thing that I did was also just opening a map and see, okay, well, very naively, what other places could copy that business model just because they're close to Panama? And I would generally say it's very tough to do. And also the geography is really only one part of the mode. I wouldn't call it a flywheel exactly, but they are
a couple of things that work together to create the mode that I see for copa. So one of them is the geography, but only because it lets copa fly the 737 and reach the whole hemisphere. So everything we already talked about, the bigger piece of the mode, in my opinion, is actually the first mover and the scale advantages they already have as the region's biggest hub. So a connecting hub is obviously only worth anything once it's already big, right? So it's a kind of, you know, chicken and egg problem.
You need a lot of travelers to create a dense system, but you need a dense system to attract a lot of travelers. So if you actually wanted to challenge Copa today, you would have to send up something like 80 destinations and all the frequencies between them more or less at once and just burn cash for years without any profits to show for it. So just to get the starting line where the network effect would eventually kick in. You know, it does remind me of the dynamic.
between Uber and Lyft, where generally speaking, they can both charge the same rate for a ride. Yet for Uber, that ride will add profitably to their bottom line, whereas for Lyft, it adds to their losses, which seems like it doesn't make sense. But the reason it happens is because Uber has reached a scale that Lyft hasn't. So the way the costs are spread out is more advantageous, basically, for Uber. But I don't want to drag us back into a discussion of operating leverage. But anyways,
My conclusion from what you're describing is basically that this is a classic network effects trap where it's very, very hard to compete with a dominant competitor once they have an existing position in the market. That's only how the dynamic seems to be. And you know, it's also proven just by the track record of the financials. They look fantastic for the last 20, 30 years. So it very apparently seems to be impossible to copy what they have. The second barrier, which is also really hard to disrupt, is pricing.
As we said, Copa has a sub six cent cost base, you know, based on chasm, what we talked about earlier, this probably most important metric in the industry. So it would be almost impossible for competitor to actually run more efficiently, which means you would be burning even more money trying to catch up because Copa can just lead the competition out and undercut their prices the whole way. Obviously, the downside there is that if companies should come in and be ready to burn a lot of money over a couple of years,
it would still result in a margin drag for many years for Copa. So even if Copa survives and the competitor goes bankrupt, eventually there will be a series of years with margin pressure. And as we talked about before, bankruptcies don't happen in the island industry as naturally as they do in other industries. Taxes and currency are also a big advantage. Panama doesn't tax foreign source income, which is basically all of Copa's income.
because their passengers are mostly flying between two other countries. And so Panama also uses the US dollar. So there's no currency risk and no capital controls that you have to worry about. And that is a big difference maker when you're talking about an emerging markets region of the world. No tax on foreign income sounds like I might need to look at some house prices in Panama. I'm just kidding. It's certainly true if it's an advantage that most competitors can obviously not compete with. And as you said before that, we always try to balance out
our exposure to these emerging markets. So if you're on the market that actually uses US dollars and it's kind of packed to that system, it obviously helps a lot from an investor standpoint. And then last but not least, this is also a business built on trust and relationships. So you know, flat routes are basically always negotiated government to government and generally require the airline to be nationally owned and controlled. So Panama has spent only decades building all of these relationships and I just don't see Costa Rica or
pretty much anyone else in the region to replicate that anytime soon. Actually, you also see that Costa Rica is going in another direction. So they are growing their air capacity faster than Panama is right now, but mostly focused on tourism. So, you know, people fly to Costa Rica for vacation, not to pass through it, which is the case for Panama. And I guess for many other Latin American countries, the political instability and the fact that many of them are already sanctioned in some way, shape or form makes it almost impossible.
for them to step up and take Panama's role in being central to air travel from North to South America. That's outlooks. I mean, the one country I thought might have a shot is actually Puerto Rico, but uses the US legal system and the US dollar, but you don't have to pay US waiters. So, you know, very similar profile to Panama, although it's a bit of a detour to, you know, get there compared to Panama. And apparently American Airlines tried running a San Juan hub before
and then ended up shutting it down after a couple of years. So probably I think the biggest competitive risk is just ultra low cost carriers getting longer range airplanes and then start flying the most important routes point to point basically skipping the hub entirely. So I think that's kind of a risk that I could think about. But then you again running into the problem that I described before where you got to fly these longer routes and then you basically have to leave people on the ground because otherwise your fuel is not enough to take the entire route. So
This is just by nature way less efficient than what Copa is doing. So it's not only about a competitor doing what Copa does better. It's more about the whole hub and spoke model becoming less relevant. Again, I don't think it's realistic anytime soon, but that's somewhat of a risk that I could see potentially in the future. And so it actually reminds me of something Ryanair CEO Michael O'Leary said in an interview that you shared with me earlier. And he basically said he will never be beaten at his own game.
which is delivering the cheapest flights. But one day, he will be disrupted by a company that invents beaming people from one place to another. So obviously being facetious, but long haul flights without a stop in Panama is not really beaming. But you get the point. Copa is unlikely to be beaten at its own game. But who says the game can't be reinvented? I think that's a great way to look at it. And Michael or Leigh, we interviews.
They're just always fun to watch. That's why I send that interview to you. And we often talk about borrowing CEOs on this show, but he's definitely not one of them. And at the same time, he also doesn't give me this sketchy feeling that I often get when CEOs are a bit more outgoing, maybe a bit too confident. But yeah, I mean, the fact that coppers yield, which is basically the average revenue an airline generates per paying passenger per mile of loan has been dropping over the last couple of years does suggest that there's at least some more competitive pressure.
starting to show up. Perhaps it's a good time then to zoom in more on the risks. Yep, we should do it. And we already talked about the industry. So I felt like a lot of the risks were covered by just COPA operating in an industry that we kind of rented on for 30 minutes. But I would say the biggest one by a long ways fuel. We talked about this before, but fuel is a huge cost that airlines basically can control. So for COPA, jet fuel is again around a quarter of revenue. And the interesting thing is that COPA actually doesn't hatch its fuel.
which is something that many other airlines do right now, again, being one of them. Maybe you can just quickly explain for the audience what hedging fuel actually means and then why COPA doesn't do it. Hedging basically means buying financial contracts that lock in or cap what you will pay for fuel in the future. So you're essentially buying an insurance against the fuel price going up. And COPA has chosen, as a matter of policy, to just pay the spot market price for fuel
whatever that happens to be in. While hatching somewhat sounds like a no-brainer on paper, it can actually be quite costly because imagine fuel prices drop a lot, but you've got a contract that forces you to keep buying it at the old higher price. Your first instinct might be, well, you probably have chosen a price where you still earn a pretty good margin, so you should survive that. But the problem is, because all the other airlines can now buy fuel cheaper, they can just undercut you on ticket pricing. So hatching has also
Some form of cost, you know that comes from it and many airlines have lost a lot of money over the years by hatching the exposure to fuel price. So again, there's no right or wrong answer about this. It's one of those tricky things about the airline business. And just to put some math behind it, Copa burns something like 380 million gallons of jet fuel a year. So if the jet fuel price moves by just $1 a gallon, that's roughly $380 million straight through operating profit.
up or down. And Kopa's total operating profit is in the range of $800-something million. So a $1 move in the fuel price swings something like half of this company's entire operating income. Well, just to emphasize again, the potential downsides of hedging is that, imagine COVID, right? They're probably in 2019 thinking, oh man, if we can hedge oil prices so that we're paying an average of $60 per barrel in 2020.
That's great. We've secured profitable economics for us. And then, well, guess what? Future prices for oil went negative in 2020. And so you're sitting there thinking that you get this great rate that you're locked into and then all of a sudden prices could drop dramatically. And it's kind of like getting a mortgage, except you don't necessarily have the option to refinance. You're locking into a commitment on a rate and then if rates fall, you're kind of like, oh, well, I'm stuck. And so
For somebody who has no familiarity with jet fuel prices, which I know are derivative of the cost of oil, but I don't know if they're more volatile and exactly what the correlation is. And so I guess my question for you is, is a $1 swing in a barrel of jet fuel? Is that a lot? I mean, does it happen frequently? It doesn't sound crazy to me. But if that happens every few months, not hedging that seems like economic suicide to me.
Yeah, no, a $1 swing is quite extreme. So just for perspective from 2005 to 2021, the price was always between $2 and $2.50 for the jet fuel. So then I think it spiked in April to $5 because of everything that happened in the world and is now coming down to the 350s. So something like that point being a $1 swing usually happens only once every decade or so. Right. And you actually talked about how
COVID was obviously a huge thing for everyone who did hedge the fuel costs and Copa is one of the very few companies in the industry that didn't go bankrupt. And obviously part of that is because they didn't sit on a contract where they had to buy fuel 80% higher than you know currently trades had. They could just basically pull as much fuel as they wanted to put into the inventory and then obviously have a pretty good business for the next couple of years. Although obviously you also have a lot of uncertainty, especially out of COVID. Now looking back at it, it always seems easy and you would just
bought as much fuel as you could because you know how it ends up going after two or three years back then. There were a whole lot of people. I still remember that the thought of flying will not go back to where it has been for the next 10 or 20 years. So it turned out differently. But you know, nobody knows. Another risk worth talking about is the Boeing relationship. So as I said, Copa has a big order book of 737 Max aircraft stretching out over the next several years, which
is a multi-billion dollar commitment. And on one hand, those new planes are good for them because, you know, obviously they're more fuel efficient than what they are replacing. And they help hold that famous cost line down on the other hand, though, it is a huge capital commitment, right? And Boeing's recent, let's say, track record on actually delivering an aircraft on time has been pretty shaky. So they have had to revise delivery targets more than just once. So Copa is partly dependent on a supplier that
I would say cautiously, hasn't exactly been reliable, both for its growth plan and also for a fleet when you're like, we already saw with the 2024 Max 9 grounding, what it looks like when a Boeing problem basically becomes Copa's problem overnight. So I also heard there is something going on in Venezuela for Copa's operations at some point. What is that all about?
Yeah, so on Venezuela there was a flight suspension that started in July 2024 since the Venezuelan government felt that countries like Panama or for example also the Dominican Republic interfered with their politics and After that ban was lifted. There were more suspensions last year obviously after the US declared the airspace and no fly zone so without going into all the details
This is an emerging market play and that can and most likely always will be surprises, I guess. So, Copa has played down, obviously, the Venezuela exposure over the years and it's been written down and also de-risk. So this is more of a known contain problem than something that's, you know, going to surprise anyone now investing into the company. But still Venezuela and Colombia together are still around 12 percent of Copa's capacity. So any volatility there obviously is a factor for you as an investor.
Then the other big risk that comes from this is concentration risk, which is really just the flip side of the bull case. So, Copa's biggest strength, having this one perfect hub at the perfect position, is also its single biggest point of failure because the entire company basically depends on that one airport in one city, in one country, and anything that disrupts Tokuman or any kind of unfavorable shift in, let's say, the Panamanian government policy,
could change the way that the business works. So there's no diversification to fall back on. So in a way, the mode and the concentration risk are kind of the same fact just looked at from two different sides. I think we just recently had a call in our mass of my community about Universal and we talked about that basically many of the things that you looked at positively for the company could also be from another angle be looked at as a more negative point. So for example, signing just the biggest artists
And you would say, you know, that's a positive thing because of Taylor Swift assigned with Universal, a lot of these smaller artists also want to be in that ecosystem where somebody else could say, well, who cares about where Taylor Swift is signed? The fact of the matter is that that deal is most likely not profitable for Universal. So there are always like two sides of the same story. Yeah, absolutely. You know, I have to say that it is remarkable how Copa handled all of these things in the past. And I think it certainly speaks to
management and the company's operational excellence. It does seem like Coppo was able to get out of the rat race that the average airline is consumed by it. I mean, looking at the returns on capital and equity as well as the margins and growth, it's not a tech stock, but I would not have guessed that this was an airline. And they have been doing that for such a long time. I mean, if this was a five-year track record, I would have discounted its value and said,
let's wait a couple of years and we'll see it behave like pretty much every other airline eventually. But Copa is doing this for many decades now. So this model clearly works. Well, talking about the management team, how about we dig deeper into that and also the capital allocation and culture and all those sort of things. And so you mentioned that the CEO Pedro Helbron has been the CEO for 38 years in a row, which is incredible.
That would be, you know, an incredible achievement at any company, but it's even more impressive at least in my books if it does happen at an airline, right? I don't know if there's a similar culture of firing coaches in basketball or American football, but in European football, it's relatively common for a coach to be let go of after only a year or two, if even, especially if you know he works at a struggling club. And I think it's somewhat similar in business. So surviving in the airline for 38 years.
is kind of like surviving one of the most demanding and struggling clubs as a coach for decades. So interestingly, and that's some unnecessary football trivia, but clubs that keep their coaches for a very long time tend to do better. And I do believe that it's the same in business. I believe that Heilbronn's tenure is pretty much the explanation for most of the things we now admire for this business. So you know, there's extreme consistency on keeping the cost low. The
refusal to ever give up on the time crown. So the completion factor of the flights and also the decision to, as we said, survive COVID intact, whether than just restructure and also maybe as a last point, with this expansion into markets like Europe or Asia just for growth sake. Actually, I think he once joked on an earnings call that there is a loaded gun that should be used if they ever decide to go into the European market. That could have come from Michael O'Leary, too, right?
It could have 100%. I don't know. I think there seems to be something about airline CEOs. They have a lot of personality. Because you have to have a sense of humor to decide to go into that business. That must be it. That must be it. But jokes aside, if you are a corporate shareholder, you must really trust this guy because he's not only the CEO, but since mid-2025, he's also the chairman of the board. So he controls a good portion of the voting shares of the stock too. So basically if you buy a corporate, you have to trust him.
Okay, so that implies that there's a dual share structure. Is that right? Yeah, exactly. So the shares that trade on the New York Stock Exchange, the ones that you know, you or I could actually buy, those are so-called class A shares, but the voting control runs through a separate class of super voting class B shares. And all of those are held by a Panamanian entity called CIASA and CIASA in turn.
is controlled by a small group of Panamanian family. So that's the Mota family, the Highbron family, the family of the CEO and the Arias families plus some other allied shareholders. And those families are basically connected with Panamanian banking insurance and also some other businesses that Copa deals with. So it's somewhat of a different dynamic than what we're used to from a Western company, for example. So what I like, I would say is that they're all pretty aligned with shareholders through their large insider stakes.
They also make most of their money through dividends, so their pay itself is pretty small. I think the combined cash bonus, including stock grants for the entire management team, is less than $10 million. So they make their money when either the stock is going up or when the dividend stays high. Going over to capital allocation, how has management done on that front in your view? Since copper operates in an industry that is prone to bankruptcies,
I personally pay a lot of attention to the balance sheet first and the copas looks pretty good. I mean, it's adjusted net debt to EBITDA is about 0.6 to 0.7 times. And to put that into perspective, most airlines are considered healthy when they sit around two to three times net debt to EBITDA. And interest is also relatively low. So I think it's about 4% on the interest that they have to pay and considering the billion dollars of cash on the balance sheet.
And the interest coverage ratio is about nine, which means nothing more than there's plenty of cash to service that and the interest. That's right. And besides though, keeping some cash for rainy days, where is COPA investing its money? The first priority is certainly we investing into the fleet. Second, I would say is then dividend, which I don't expect to change given that this is how the management team makes most of its money. And then if there's cash left over, they also occasionally buy back shares. So the fleet
You know, just cost them a lot of money recently, we just talked about the order book with Boeing. So they've got this 737 max order that we mentioned, which is about $900 million in order volume, and it has to be paid over the next two and a half years. So that's also why free cash flow has seen a sharp drop this year. And operating cash flow is still at, you know, all time high. So there's no structural change to how the business works.
even though obviously if you just look at some cash flow metrics, it doesn't look as good anymore as it looked half a year ago. And do they plan to keep paying the dividend considering this big investment in a new fleet? I'm pretty sure they will. Yes. Again, like even through a COVID, they still kept the dividend and they were paying it throughout all of the other things we discussed, the max grounding and all of that sort of stuff. It's just an incentive, right? If you make most of your money with the dividend, if you're the management team,
Obviously, you are hugely incentivized to keep that dividend alive and make sure that all of the decisions that you make in regards to investments and spending money do not threaten the dividend. I think that covers the whole business now. And so we've talked about the industry, the mode, the risks, the management and capital allocation.
That means it's time to go to everybody's favorite question and that is, what is this business worth? What is the intrinsic value? And do we actually want to buy an airline for our intrinsic value portfolio that we manage through this show? I gotta say, I thought it might be hard to value an airline, which is basically part of why investing in airlines is so difficult. But Co-Plan's financials are so stable that it doesn't even feel like you're valuing an airline. In my base case is
basically business as usual, which is a good thing to say. One of you can say with confidence that you underwrite the past financials. That's a pretty good thing to say. And that's actually what I expect for Kopa. So I have revenue going at about 7%, which is the median growth rate of the last decade. And I keep margins more or less stable to potentially lower in the next two years because of what we currently see with the fuel prices. But I do expect that they would go back in the three years following that over my estimated five year time horizon.
I don't expect a mix shift towards more revenue from the loyalty program or the cargo. Maybe that happens and it's more meaningful than I anticipated, but I doubt that it will have a measurable impact on the business at least in the next five years. And then I have the dividend payout ratio at 40%, which is also in line with where it's historically been. And then I use a discount rate of 10%, slightly higher than the 8% we usually use because we talk about an airline and emerging markets. So you want to take the safe route.
And then I apply a margin of safety discount of about 20%. Yeah, I mean, the 10% discount makes sense because you're accounting for the different risks that come with operating in Latin America versus investing in a large cap US equity, where there is also still risk, but probably less so in terms of the sort of exogenous factors that you can't control. And all of that is obviously also
a huge part or influence on the multiple rate. When I initially say that this company is trading at eight times earnings, it seems like it's incredibly cheap. But compared to what other airlines trade at, especially in the emerging markets, it's actually pretty much in line with what I would also expect going forward. So I have a multiple of nine, which I believe is fair for such a high quality company. And if you have all of these assumptions, I get an expected return of about 15%, including the 5% dividend yield that we currently see.
Okay, that's pretty good. That's pretty good. So what about the bull and bear case out of those factor? I did do both of them and you can find them in the model, which by the way, you can always find our models and our portfolio in our free investing newsletter. That's also where you can find updates on all of the portfolio holding. So we do not only talk about a portfolio, we also share it. And I'm just saying that because I'm constantly getting asked why we won't share the portfolio that we're always talking about in the episodes. We do share it.
Of course, and again, it's in the intrinsic value newsletter, but I will also include a link to the Google Sheets in the show notes of this episode so you can find every single position that we own in the portfolio. You can find our performance and you can also find our watch lists, so all the companies that we covered on the show that haven't yet made it into the portfolio. But getting back to the variation, I don't think it's necessary to walk through the bull and the bear case here on this show in detail. Ultimately, I adjusted the growth rates and the margins in both cases.
The way to lose money on Copa, if you just want to summarize it, is if net margins drop into the low teens range. And at that point, the stock has only worth something in the 60 to 80 dollar range. How could that happen? Well, either because this strategy of not hatching fuel costs turns out to be wrong in this environment, or if all of the stuff that we discussed today suddenly stops working, which I consider to be highly unlikely. So I get the feeling, though, that you came away with a pretty positive feeling from your research about Copa.
I did. Yes. I mean, you know, that doesn't mean that I would recommend adding copper at these prices to our portfolio. I think I just need a bit of a bigger margin of safety on this. And I know I'm somewhat, you know, using an excuse here to not add the first airline to our portfolio. But I don't know. There's still so much uncertainty about fuel costs right now. We have all of this geopolitical tension that certainly has a huge impact on the price. And again, copper does not hatch it.
with Reiner, for example, they already have a hedge in place. So you know that at least for the next six months, they won't have a problem with costs. And I don't criticize Cobra for doing that because, you know, they've done that for 20, 30, 40 years and it has always worked out in significantly more difficult times than today. But for me personally, looking at this situation and also the fact that the stock again has run up to a P of like eight, I do think I would like a bit more of a margin of safety. And I personally think that at about $100 per share.
this would be a highly interesting opportunity. To be clear, never thought I would say this, but I could actually see myself investing in an airline with Copa, but I would probably want to do it in the next crisis, right? The next time there's a big fear of global war or pandemic or financial crisis, I mean, Copa would actually probably be on my list to buy based on how they've survived past crises. And, you know, if you bought the stock during any of those past tips, if you just look at the chart, you can see that you would have done incredibly well
to say nothing of the compounding benefit of this very appealing dividend at nearly a 5% yield and current prices. And that would only increase if the stock goes down further. And so for an airline average of 14% total return keger over a decade, 14% a year, I mean, that's really surprising. And it challenges my prior assumptions about the industry, honestly, or at least what can be possible in this industry despite all the bad things you hear.
With all that said, when I look at the company's PE multiple though, and more than eight times earnings or nine times earnings, while that does sound relatively cheap to the other companies we've covered, where sometimes they're 30, 40 times earnings, the multiple here is not historically cheap for COPA. So if you look back over the last 10 or 15 years, and ADEX multiple is about exactly in line with the median valuation for the stock. And while I think the stock market can be distorted in the short term,
for a mature business, I see a lot of value actually in looking at the median valuation over a decade plus period. I find that to be pretty informative of what a fair valuation, fair multiple to pay for businesses. Over a decade, the market on average is probably more right about valuing the stock than it is wrong. And so I do think the stock at the moment is priced fairly, but also I think it's priced attractively at current levels. And then simultaneously,
For me to overcome my own biases against airlines, and this is really just a personal issue, and the fragility of their business model, especially with unhedged fuel costs, I just think I would need to feel like I was getting an absolutely bargain price. So if I was trading at five times earnings, for example, that would probably be all over this thing. But for now, though, and I truly mean this, I would love to keep it on top of our watch list and revisit it, perhaps down the road.
I couldn't have wished for more than turning one of the most bearish investors on airlines and to someone who could actually see themselves owning a Copa in our portfolio. I agree. I think especially for such an industry, there will be a chance to buy this company at five times earnings again. And when that's the case, we've done the work and we're willing to invest in it. So I'm pretty happy with how this turned out. Not only did I learn a ton about the industry that I didn't look at prior, but also I found a pretty good company.
With that, let me close it for today with a quote. I actually wanted to use one, Baraner CEO Michael O'Leary. But I'm not kidding. I couldn't find one which didn't use the F word or insulted an entire country's people. So let's go with one by former Delta airline CEO Colin Woolman, who said running an airline is like having a baby fun to conceive, but held to deliver. What a line. I guess it's true that all of these airline CEOs have a very special sense of comedy. But
On that note, it's been a fun day, Daniel. I enjoyed the pitch. You've opened my eyes to the airline industry. Maybe some of the listeners feel the same way. We'll see you all again next time. Thanks for listening to TIP. Follow the Investors Podcast on your favorite podcast app and visit theinvestorpodcast.com for show notes and educational resources. This podcast is for informational and entertainment purposes only and does not provide financial, investment, tax or legal advice.
The content is impersonal and does not consider objectives, financial situation, or needs. Investing involves risk including possible loss of principle and past performance is not a guarantee of future results. Listeners should do their own research and consult a qualified professional before making any financial decisions. Nothing on this show is a recommendation or solicitation to buy or sell any security or other financial product.
hosts, guests, and the Investors' Podcast Network may hold positions in securities discussed and may change those positions at any time without notice. References to any third-party products, services, or advertisers do not constitute endorsements, and the Investors' Podcast Network is not responsible for any claims made by them. Copyright by the Investors' Podcast Network. All rights reserved.